So today's דף daf is י"ז yud zayin and we pick up
on the משנה mishnah on the bottom of ט"ו עמוד ב' tes
vav amud bet and we had some fascinating גמרא gemara before about
the הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, מסורה, mesorah, now we turn
it back to a straight discussion about תמורה, temurah, but it's interesting
we've been doing it in the framework of a type of a
comparison contrast, you know, comparing קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur to קרבנות יחיד,
korbanos yachid, and now we're going to do another type of a
comparison, תמורה temurah to being to sanctifying original sanctity because of course
that makes a lot of sense, תמורה temurah you try to transfer
sanctity you wind up sanctifying, how is that similar dissimilar in terms
of the effect, obviously it's prohibited but in terms of the effect
to a direct act of sanctification. So let's take a look at
the משנה mishnah ט"ו עמוד ב'. tes vav amud bet. חומר בקדשים
מבתמורה וחומר בתמורה מובקדשים, chomer bekodshim mibetemurah vechomer betemurah mibekodshim, there is
greater weight sometimes in sanctifying קדשים kodshim could mean sacrifices, sanctified objects,
but it really means the act of sanctification than in the act
of תמורה, temurah, and sometimes there's greater weight in the act of
תמורה temurah than the act of sanctifying. חומר בקדשים מבתמורה שהקדשים עושה
תמורה ואין תמורה עושה תמורה. chomer bekodshim mibetemurah shehakodshim ose temurah ve'ein
temurah osa temurah. Oh excuse me, I jumped ahead, actually no, the
first thing we are pointing to is the actual object, the animal.
So there's greater weight of sanctified animals, directly sanctified animals from תמורה
temurah and sometimes from תמורה temurah from directly sanctified. So how is
it? So the greater weight in sanctified animals, directly sanctified, is that
directly sanctified animals
you can make a תמורה temurah from them, ואין תמורה עושה תמורה,
ve'ein temurah osa temurah, you can't make a תמורה temurah from a
תמורה temurah and this is a point that we have said before.
So only the original animal not the תמורה, temurah, you can't daisy
chain it. הציבור והשותפים מקדישים אבל לא ממירים, hatzibur vehashutfim makdishim aval
lo memirim,
now we get to the act of sanctification, a community and partners
can sanctify אבל לא ממירים, aval lo memirim, they can't do a
תמורה. temurah. Okay, we just said before an animal owned by
that has been sanctified by a ציבור tzibur or by partners, you
cannot do a תמורה temurah from it. So you could focus on
the animal which was sort of the previous contrast, that an animal
owned by meaning you don't do a תמורה temurah on a קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, on a קרבן שותפים, korban shutfim, but this is
actually also talking about the act, the ציבור tzibur and the שותפים
shutfim do not do תמורה temurah whereas but they can sanctify.
Of course they can sanctify, that's how you make a קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibur, you buy it with communal funds. That's how you make
a קרבן שותפים korban shutfim is that partners actually sanctify, they don't
necessarily both utter the words, one of them does it for the
partnership, but as partners they sanctify. So partners and the ציבור tzibur
can sanctify and but they cannot make a
תמורה. temurah. ומקדישים עוברים
ואיברים אבל לא ממירים, umakdishim ubarim ve'eivarim aval lo memirim, you can
sanctify fetuses and limbs אבל
לא ממירים, aval lo memirim, you cannot do תמורה temurah from as
from fetuses or limbs or to fetuses and limbs and if you
remember we had a whole big סוגיא sugya about that before. Okay,
but you can sanctify fetuses and limbs, you cannot do תמורה temurah
from them or to them because it says בהמה בבהמה, behemah bibehemah,
you have to be starting with a full בהמה behemah and ending
with a full בהמה. behemah. חומר בתמורה מובקדשים, chomer betemurah mibekodshim, so
that's the way in which sanctifying has the actually sanctified animals can
sometimes have greater weight, they can be a source of תמורה temurah
and the act of sanctifying has broader scope than the act of
תמורה. temurah. תמורה temurah cannot be with ציבור, tzibur, cannot be with
limbs, cannot be with fetuses and so on. Now, חומר בתמורה מובקדשים,
chomer betemurah mibekodshim, there are ways in תמורה temurah is greater than
is weightier than קדשים. kodshim. שהקדושה חלה על בעל מום קבוע ואינו
יוצא לחולין לגזז ולעבוד. shehakedusha chala al ba'al mum kavua ve'eino yotze
lechulin legazez vela'avod. Why? Because if you try to now it's sort
of the phrasing isn't so good because it really and if you
take a look at the הגהות הב"ח hagahot habach has a correction
of this, שהתמורה חלה shehatemurah chala not שהקדושה חלה. shehakedusha chala. Okay,
because this is the way in which תמורה temurah is weightier, that
the sanctity of the
תמורה temurah takes effect even on an animal with a fixed blemish.
And that animal does not go out to be sheared and worked.
What does this mean? So this is the thing we keep on
coming back to, that if you sanctify an animal that's unblemished, direct
sanctity, and then it gets a blemish, you can't bring it as
a קרבן, korban, what do you do? You redeem it. What's the
status of the animal afterwards? It's קדשים שנפסלו kodshim shenifsulu and it
has a there's some remnant of the קדושה, kedusha, you can't work
it, you can't shear it. Let's say you sanctify the animal from
the beginning with a blemish, then what would be the status there?
Well, if it had a blemish from the beginning, it was never
fit, so it's like you sanctified your car, it's like you sanctified
your woodpile, and you can just redeem it and it has no
קדושה kedusha that remains because it never got a קדושת הגוף. kedushat
haguf. In this way תמורה temurah is different. Since we learned before
from a פסוק, pasuk, רע בטוב או טוב ברע, ra betov o
tov bera,
that you can't switch good for bad, bad for good, and חז"ל
chazal understand bad means with a blemish, and therefore they're saying if
you do it, even if the animal had a blemish, either animal,
it has the same תמורה, temurah, it has the same קדושה kedusha
as the original. So from there we say that if you do
תמורה temurah from an unblemished animal to one. With a blemish, the
Torah says והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש. Vehayah hu utemurato yiheyeh kodesh.
So what the Torah is telling you is that the קדושה kedusha
does take effect even on this blemished animal, even though it started
by being blemished, is a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Now you can't
bring it as a קרבן, korban, of course, you can never bring
an animal with a blemish as a קרבן, korban, but it has
the same קדושה kedusha as the original and therefore even now if
you were to when you redeem this one with the blemish, this
תמורה tmura with a blemish, it will still have this residual קדושה.
kedusha. So as opposed again to originally sanctifying, where if you originally
sanctified one with a blemish, it has no קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
and when you remove it there's no residual קדושה, kedusha, this one
because it's derived from the תמורה tmura and the Torah tells you
it's going to be sanctified like the תמורה tmura even when it
started with a blemish, it has קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf and even
when you remove it there's residual קדושה. kedusha. Okay, so that's the
way in which תמורה tmura is weightier. Let's keep on going. רבי
יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda omer, now all of that
interestingly the גמרא's Gemara not going to discuss any of that because
all that we've already discussed. So the whole focus of the גמרא
Gemara is going to be on the end of this משנה mishna
starting with this point. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose berabbi
Yehuda omer, עשה שוגג כמזיד בתמורה ולא עשה שוגג כמזיד במוקדשין. asah
shogeg kemezid betmura velo asah shogeg kemezid bemukdashin. By תמורה tmura unintentional
is made like intentional, but not by originally sanctifying. The גמרא's Gemara
going to have a lot of fun figuring out what that means,
we'll get to that in one minute. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, הכלאים והטרפה והיוצא דופן והטומטום והאנדרוגינוס לא קדושים ולא מקדישים. hakilayim
vehaterifa vehayotzei dofen vehatumtum veha'androgynos lo kedoshim velo makdishim. Although we sort
of said before, yes we did, that was quoted, but now we're
having it in the משנה, mishna, although we said before that תמורה
tmura takes effect on a בעל מום, ba'al mum, there are some
things that are worse than a בעל מום, ba'al mum, different than
a בעל מום, ba'al mum, things like mixed breeds, טרפה, treifa, an
animal that's going to die, has a wound, יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen,
Caesarean section, or טומטום אנדרוגינוס, tumtum androgynos, uncertain or mixed gender. All
of these things do not be sanctified as an object of תמורה,
tmura, the sanctity will not take effect on them, and they do
not sanctify other things. Now it does not mean by the way
that they cannot be sanctified at all, it means like we said
before, not
קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. There would still be קדושת דמים, kedushat damim,
it would still be like you sanctify your car, okay, but it
would not be a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. However, that's if you
directly try to sanctify them. However, if you try to make them
a תמורה, tmura, you know, that we will see that's like a
whole that they surely cannot become part of the process of תמורה,
tmura, either to receive the קדושה kedusha
or to be the source of the קדושה. kedusha. So we will
see that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara now that starts with the first issue
about שוגג כמזיד. shogeg kemezid. Okay, מאי טעמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה?
mai ta'ameih deRabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda? What's the reasoning of רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda? אמר קרא, amar kra, it says
שוגג כמזיד shogeg kemezid because the פסוק pasuk says יהיה קדש, yiheyeh
kodesh, יהיה קדש, yiheyeh kodesh, it shall be קדש. kodesh. I don't
know what else it could have said, קדש kodesh I guess maybe
without the יהיה. yiheyeh. Okay, לרבות שוגג כמזיד, lerabot shogeg kemezid,
so that extra thing is telling you unintentional is like intentional. היכי
דמי שוגג כמזיד? heichi dami shogeg kemezid? How are they similar? Now
here you will see by just quickly glancing at the גמרא, Gemara,
there are tons of corrections and different sort of versions here, you
see all the little parentheses and notes and notations etc. So I
will just tell you from the outset what the big question is.
There are two parts of תמורה tmura as we know, we've always
been focused on one of them. One is that there's a prohibition
to do the act of תמורה, tmura, the other is that it
takes effect, that the other animal becomes sanctified. We've always been focused
on the latter. Now when you say שוגג כמזיד, shogeg kemezid, that
word שוגג כמזיד shogeg kemezid are words that normally focus on the
actor and on the way to which you are a willful
violator, מזיד, mezid, or a שוגג, shogeg, an unintentional, negligent but unintentional
violator. The question here is what is the import of רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה's Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda statement? Is he refocusing our attention
back to the act of תמורה tmura and saying that idea that
you get lashes, sometimes even though normally you only get lashes if
you're מזיד, mezid, sometimes you can get lashes even if you're שוגג
shogeg and that's part of the חידוש chidush of תמורה. tmura. That's
and then we're going to have a list of cases. That's one
way of understanding it. The other way of understanding him is that
no, we're not talking about lashes, lashes is only for מזיד. mezid.
We're still talking about the effect, that the effect of תמורה tmura
will sometimes occur even in cases of error, not only in cases
when you know when you're doing. So there is if as we
read the גמרא, Gemara, you will see there are different versions of
whether the text is קדוש kadosh and לא קדוש lo kadosh or
לוקה lokeh and לא לוקה. lo lokeh. And if you want to
take a quick look at this first תוספות Tosafot even before we
get to the cases in the גמרא, Gemara, גבי תמורה לוקה גבי
קדשים לא לוקה, gabei tmura lokeh gabei kodashim lo lokeh, that's going
to be one of the first lines. תוספות Tosafot says ואיכא ספרים
דגרסי ve'ika sefarim degarsi גבי תמורה קדיש וגבי קדשים לא קדיש. gabei
tmura kadish vegabei kodashim lo kadish. Okay, and then he basically says
that there were two בעלי התוספות, ba'alei hatosafot, רבינו שמשון Rabbeinu Shimshon
and I forget who the other one was, רב שמשון משאנץ Rav
Shimshon miShantz and רבינו ברוך, Rabbeinu Baruch, and one consistently said it's
about getting lashes and the other consistently said it's about being sanctified
and they basically they either they chose different גרסאות girsa'ot of the
גמרא Gemara or they started with different גרסאות girsa'ot of the גמרא
Gemara but they came from two very different approaches. So there's a
major question on whether this section is about getting lashes or is
it about can you get lashes even if you're שוגג shogeg or
is it all about the effect about being קדוש kadosh or לא
קדוש. lo kadosh. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
ואיכא דאמרי ve'ika de'amri it's all effect as קדושה kedusha check check
קדושה. kedusha. חלה *chala* that you know since it would be the
same. Maybe, but he says שוגג shogeg. מזיד *shogeg mezid* are words
that seem to that- that normally would not be used when you're
talking about effect. Talking about effect you might say תופס *tofes* or
not תופס *tofes* and so on. Let's take a look. היכי דמי
שוגג shogeg. למזיד *Heichi dami shogeg lemezid*? What are the examples? Back
to the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. אמר חזקיה קסבר שמותר להמיר *Amar Chizkiya
kasavar shemutar lehamir*. He thought it was allowed to do it. Okay,
אומר מותר *omer mutar*. גבי תמורה לקי, גבי קדשים לא לקי gabi
tmura laki gabi kodshim lo laki. *Gabi tmura laki, gabi kodshim lo
laki*. Our version is by תמורה tmura *tmura* you got lashes, by
קדשים kodshim *kodshim* you don't get lashes. Now, the very fact that
we're contrasting it to קדשים kodshim *kodshim*, when would I ever get
lashes for קדשים kodshim? *kodshim*? How's it even relevant to do the
comparison contrast? If I sanctify? No, there is a way I can
get lashes for sanctifying. Do you remember? We discussed it before. When
you get lashes for doing an act of sanctification? Oh, oh, right,
right. It's pop quiz, pop quiz. This is 10% of your final
grade. בזמן הזה *Bazman hazeh*? No, no, no, no. Sanctifying a בעל
מום ba'al mum, *baal mum*. המקדיש בעל מום ba'al mum? *Hamakdish baal
mum* is a לאו lav *lav* and according to the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* when your actions have an effect even if it's דיבור *dibbur*
it's לקי *laki*. We discussed this before. So, according to that we're
comparing two ways in which you could מקדיש makdish *makdish* and get
lashes. One is an act of תמורה tmura *tmura*, the other is
being מקדיש makdish *makdish* with a בעל מום ba'al mum. *baal mum*.
And even with there, if it's normal being מקדיש makdish *makdish*, okay,
if you're שוגג shogeg, *shogeg*, unintentional, you don't get lashes. Whereas by
תמורה tmura *tmura*, יהיה קדש *yiyeh kodesh* is coming to tell me
although again the word יהיה *yiyeh* is emphasizing the effect, not the
act, according to this way of reading the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, this
גירסא *girsa* of גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, יהיה *yiyeh* means you get lashes
even for an unintentional act. Okay, so that's one way of reading.
The other way of reading is that we're not talking again about
lashes, we're talking about the effect. Now if we're talking about the
effect, it's a little bizarre. Why would I ever think that אומר
מותר *omer mutar* would stop the effect? Is that really true? If
I really take an animal with a מום mum, *mum* and I
try to sanctify it, I thought it was מותר *mutar* to be
מקדיש makdish *makdish* an animal with a מום mum? *mum*. Are you
telling me it's not קדוש kadosh *kadosh*? Of course it's קדוש kadosh
*kadosh*. Why does אומר מותר *omer mutar* affect the קדושה kedusha *kedusha*?
So again this idea of אומר מותר *omer mutar* seems to really
point to the issue that they're debating whether it is whether you
get lashes or not, whether you've transgressed, well you have transgressed, but
whether it's deserving of lashes. Okay, so that's one way. That according
to this according to this even if somebody is unintentional, thinks it's
permissible, he's going to get lashes by תמורה tmura. *tmura*. Okay, and
then you could see in the in the brackets we'll just read
it to again emphasize that there are two completely different reads of
this גמרא gemara *Gemara*. לישנא אחרינא גבי תמורה קדיש גבי קדשים לא
קדיש gabi tmura kadish gabi kodshim lo kadish. *Lishna achrina gabi tmura
kadish gabi kodshim lo kadish*. Okay, but that again is a very
different on the one hand it's I side with the idea that
it's very difficult to imagine that out of nowhere here's a category
of things you get lashes for even when you're unintentional. We like
never hear about that. Okay, but on the other hand the word
שוגג shogeg. *shogeg* and מזיד *mezid* points to that. And number two,
in this case you can't understand that why an אומר מותר *omer
mutar* it shouldn't become קדוש kadosh *kadosh* by a case of קדשים
kodshim? *kodshim*, right? So cares, you still tried to sanctify the animal,
it should be sanctified. Okay, anyway so that emphasizes the question of
lashes. ריש לקיש ורבי יוחנן אמרי *Resh Lakish veRabbi Yochanan amri*, now
ריש לקיש ורבי יוחנן *Resh Lakish veRabbi Yochanan* say no, here's what
it means. By the way, it could be that some of these
cases are one and some are the other, right? There's an attempt
to read them all about sanctifying, all about getting lashes. Maybe it
depends on which of the opinions we're going to be looking at.
ריש לקיש ורבי יוחנן אמרי קסבר לומר תמורת עולה olah, ואמר תמורת
שלמים shlomim *Resh Lakish veRabbi Yochanan amri kasavar lomar tmuras olah ve'amar
tmuras shelamim*. You basically were you had two animals in front of
you, an עולה *olah* and a שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*, and you had
your cow that wasn't sanctified. And you were going to say I'm
exchanging it with my שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*. That's what you were thinking
or I'm going to exchange it with my עולה *olah*. That's what
you were thinking. But accidentally what came out of your mouth? I'm
exchanging it with my שלמים shelamim *shelamim*. So you said something that
you weren't intending. Now that normally is an issue of טעות taus,
*taos*. The word you said were in error and the normal principle
here is that קדושה kedusha בטעות לא קדושה kedushah *kedusha betaos lo
kedusha*. That if you try to sanctify something normally we say דברים
שבלב אינם דברים *devarim shebelev einam devarim*, what you're thinking doesn't matter,
it matters what you said. Okay, but by when it comes to
הפלאה *hafla'ah*, acts of sort of affecting change status through through speech,
speech acts, and sanctifying, we rule that קדושה kedushah בטעות לא קדושה
kedusha, *kedusha betaos lo kedusha*. Matters what you were thinking. So that
type of a case if I was trying to say this I
wanted to say this animal is a שלמים shelamim *shelamim* and I
accidentally I said עולה *olah*. I want to say it's an עולה
*olah* accidentally I said שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. It's מחלוקת machloket בית שמאי
ובית הלל *machlokes Beis Shammai veBeis Hillel*. We rule like בית הלל
*Beis Hillel*. קדושה kedusha. בטעות לא קדושה kedusha. *Kedusha betaos lo kedusha*.
You didn't say what you wanted to say, it's not sanctified. But
if I tried to say this animal is an exchange for that
עולה *olah* and accidentally I said exchange for שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*, then
it does take effect. יהיה קדש *Yiyeh kodesh* because of יהיה קדש
*yiyeh kodesh* and even שוגג shogeg *shogeg*, even with a mistake. But
why are we trying to get you to do a sin? You
know what I mean? We're not trying to get you to do
a sin. We're trying to understand we're trying to understand what the
effect of the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* is. I would say more anyway
it's about the mechanics. If I am trying to create קדושה kedusha
*kedusha* from scratch, so that's a particular הפלאה *hafla'ah* act and the
words have to match what's in my mouth, it has to be
a real act that changes status. Here I already have קדושה kedusha
*kedusha*. It requires a lot less to transfer that to another animal.
You say reason for example it can take effect on a בעל
מום ba'al mum, *baal mum*. So I would not say we're trying
to get you to sin, I would say it's easier for the
act to have effect because you're starting with a source of קדושה
kedusha, *kedusha* rather than creating it from scratch. Okay, now this answer
clearly points to the issue not of lashes but to the effect
of the act. Okay, so different answers seem to point to different
ways. So קסבר לומר תמורת עולה ואמר תמורת שלמים shelamim. גבי תמורה
gabi tmura קדיש גבי קדשים gabi kodshim, לא קדיש. By שלמים shelamim,
even though you didn't say what you were thinking, it takes effect.
By קדשים kodshim it would not. Or קסבר לומר לשחור ואמר ללבן.
kasavar lomar lishachor ve'amar lalavan. You wanted to say I'm sanctifying the
black one and instead you said the white one, or I just
wanted to say I'm switching it with the black one and instead
you said the white one. So another example where you said something
you said what you it's something that was not consistent with what
you were thinking. גבי תמורה tmura, now of course here's the question,
גבי תמורה tmura לקי גבי קדשים kodshim לא לקי. Is it about
lashes? Or is it, you know, and if you look at the
side, the גרסא girsa is גבי תמורה tmurah קדיש גבי קדשים kodashim
לא קדיש. Okay, so again with the question of what it means.
Again here, what makes more sense is the question of whether it
becomes sanctified. Because here the issue is, is קדושה בטעות קדושה? kedusha
betaus kedusha? By תמורה tmurah it is, by קדשים it is not.
And the question is not willfulness to sin, the question is whether
it was טעות, ta'ut whether you said something which was different from
what you were thinking. So you were thinking you thought it was
like, you know, you wanted to say sheep and instead you said
cow? Yeah, by תמורה tmurah yes. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar
באומר תצא זו ותכנס זו. be'omer tetzei zu vetikanes zu. That you
basically said I want this one to go out and stop being
קדוש kadosh and I want this one to become קדוש kadosh in
its stead. Now that's normally of course what תמורה tmurah, is. Okay,
so yeah, what exactly is the problem? So רש"י Rashi basically says
because what you meant very clearly is I don't want this קדושה
kedusha to take effect. I when you're trying to do תמורה. tmurah
Now always I would think that's pretty implicit, that you're trying to
say this should take the stead of that. But here you're explicit.
You say I only want this one to become קדוש kadosh, if
the other one's you know קדושה kedusha is removed. Okay, so you
would say, ah, okay, so then fine, you didn't do anything because
you stipulated. And nevertheless, and this is really a surprise, right, that
that's what we're including from יהיה קודש. yihiyeh kodesh. No, if you
try to say it's an exchange, even if you thought you could
control that process and say it won't take effect unless the other
one goes out, since you basically tried to designate it as an
exchange, it takes effect regardless. To me, so it's almost as if
you said תכנס זו אם. tikanes zu im. Right, that's the way
רש"י Rashi understands it. Okay, does it matter the stipulation? What? The
stipulation comes first or it changes it? Not, yeah, it doesn't sound
like it in the גמרא. gemara Okay, now what's the comparison to
קדשים? Where do you have that similar type of an example like
קדשים? It's never about an exchange. So it's a very this is
like the probably the the one that's the least parallel. So גבי
קדשים, what's the comparison by קדשים if you try to do something
like that? שנולד בהם מום נאכלים בלא פדיון. shenolad bahem mum ne'echalim
belo pidyon. That you think that you can get around the prohibition
or you make a mistake about the parameters of the prohibition. What's
the parameters here? So we're no longer talking about sanctifying a בעל
מום, ba'al mum we're saying that let's say you think that when
an animal has a מום, mum. you know, what do you have
to do with an animal with a מום? mum You have to
redeem it. You think that you're now maybe you think it's like
a בכור ומעשר, bechor uma'aser, you think you're allowed to eat it
once it has a מום. mum You don't have to bring it
as a קרבן. korban. So it's a very it's not as right
it's not as good as all those other cases in terms of
a direct parallel. But the logic is, you know there's a prohibition
here, but you think you can work around it. You know it's
prohibited to do תמורה, tmurah but you think oh I'm going to
stipulate it this way so I'm going to be safe. You know
there's a prohibition of of eating קדשים and that you know and
so but you think oh with a מום mum I can eat
it without redeeming it. Okay, so again what now it sounds like
we're dealing with is not a question about will it take effect,
but again about whether you're going to be punished because you are
making a mistake about the condition about the circumstances of the prohibition
or the scope of the prohibition. So that's why again our גרסא
girsa here is בלא פדיון לא לקי גבי תמורה לקי. belo pidyon
lo laki gabi tmura laki. So here it seems like it really
is more of an issue about getting lashes or not getting lashes.
Although again by תמורה tmurah, if you try to stipulate, part of
the חידוש chiddush is that it also takes effect. Okay, so that's
another comparison. What did you say about the בעל מום? ba'al mum
That you think that you're allowed to eat it without redeeming it.
A normal animal has a מום mum, and then you eat it.
I'm sorry, and then you eat it. There's no declaration involved? No,
no, no. But the similarity is is that if you focus on
the lashes, that you think you can skirt
around or you're not, you know, you know there's a problem here,
but you think somehow it's not going to apply in this case.
Okay, and who are you verbalizing to your former to take the
or the who are you verbalizing to? Is it all just internal
that you have this? So yeah, so again in the case of
you don't have to verbalize it if it's a question about that's
a good point. If it's about getting lashes, well I guess if
we say what you're thinking doesn't matter, then you don't have to
verbalize, it doesn't matter, so it doesn't. But but in the case
about eating it with a blemish, you're right. I mean if somebody
well you know you would get warning. Somebody would say you're not
allowed to do that. And if he says and you'll get lashes.
And if he says I well no I actually am allowed because
it's got a blemish. And before they have a chance to correct
him about this he goes ahead and eats it. So actually in
the case of lashes there would have to be warning and we
would and therefore we would know what you were thinking. Now if
you focus on the lashes issue, then the way what this is
most in contrast to is the first answer of the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* of אומר מותר *Omer Mutar*. And if you and then it's
actually, you know, you could understand that there's a difference here of
degree of how much of a שוגג *shogeg* you are. One person
is completely oblivious, right? I never knew you can't exchange. I figured,
you know, why can't you exchange one animal for another? And the
other person sort of knows there's a problem, but he thinks that
this doesn't apply in this case, he thinks he can get around
it. Now, which one of them is more negligent is an interesting
question. You could say that the guy who knows there's an issue,
you should find out the details if you know there's an issue.
If you're completely oblivious, then how can we expect anything? You're completely
oblivious, right? You could say the opposite. How could you be completely
oblivious? It's right there in the תורה Torah *Torah*. So anyway, whatever
the answer is though, it seems that they are saying if the
חידוש chiddush *chiddush* is you get lashes even though you're שוגג *shogeg*,
how far are we going to take that? How far are we
going to say that even if you have, you know, even if
you're very little fault, you're still going to get lashes? And it
seems that those two answers are trying to describe cases of different
degrees of negligence, different degrees of fault. Okay. Now we get another
answer that's more about the whether it takes effect and more about
the issue of error. So let's take a look. הטעות *Ha-ta'ut* is
not about שוגג *shogeg*. Let's take a look. Where are we? רב
ששת אמר באומר אכנס לבית זה ואקדיש ואמיר מדעתי *Rav Sheshet amar
be-omer ekaneis le-bayit zeh ve-akdish ve-amir mida'ati*. Somebody says, "I'm going to
go into that house and sanctify," or "I'm going to go into
the house and I'm going to do תמורה tmurah. *Temurah* intentionally, מדעתי
*mida'ati*." And then what happens? ונכנס והן להקדיש *Ve-nichnas ve-hen le-hikdish*, you
go in, you either—these are separate cases—do תמורה tmurah *Temurah* or you
sanctify שלא מדעתו *shelo mida'ato*, unintentionally. I'm going to talk about that
in a minute. So גבי תמורה tmurah, לקי גבי קדשים לא לקי
*Gabei Temurah laki gabei Kodshim lo laki*. And our גרסא girsa, *girsa*
here is lashes, but it could be the other. So at תמורה
tmurah *Temurah* you get lashes, קדשים *Kodshim* you don't. Now, how do
you do something שלא מדעתו *shelo mida'ato*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
that רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says בעל מחשבות הוא *ba'al machshavot hu*. You
know, you're a לופטמענטש *luftmensch*, you're not even aware about what you're
doing. So basically, you express your intention beforehand, "Oh, I'm planning on
going in and sanctifying," but then when you go in, you're like
your head's in the clouds, but somehow your mouth is on autopilot.
So therefore, you said, "I'm sanctifying," or you said, "I'm doing תמורה
temurah *Temurah*," but at the time your head was somewhere else. Okay,
so but you had expressed your intention before. So therefore, by תמורה
temurah *Temurah*, that's considered like an intentional act, and by קדשים *Kodshim*
it's not. Now, what is the effect of an intentional act? Again,
you could say therefore you get lashes. In קדשים *Kodshim* you don't
get lashes, by תמורה temurah *Temurah* you get lashes even though at
the moment you weren't doing it intentionally. Or you could say it's
a question about קדושה kedusha בטעות *kedushah be-ta'ut*, that by הקדש *hekdesh*,
since it was unintentional, it's like a טעות *ta'ut*, you weren't thinking
what you were saying, and by תמורה temurah *Temurah*, טעות *ta'ut* doesn't
matter and it still takes effect. So you could do it either
way. But yes, if you had to express your intention before, it
wouldn't even work by תמורה temurah? *Temurah*. So if it's about the
issue of lashes, not about the issue of טעות *ta'ut*, again it's
a question about how far can we say that if you're not
at fault, we're going to give you lashes? So we already had
two answers. One was a totally oblivious, didn't know the details. And
here the answer is you're not really completely at fault. You were
thinking about it and planning it willfully a few minutes ago. The
only thing is at that exact second you were doing it on
autopilot. So again, the way I would read this, it's not—if it
really means get lashes when you're unintentional, when you're not willful, we're
trying to narrow those cases because that's a disturbing idea that you
can get lashes even if you did not do it willfully. Yes.
So another example. So I say, "I'm going to be מחלל שבת
Shabbat *mechalel Shabbos* this שבת *Shabbos*." Right. And then I forget about
the fact that I said that and I
accidentally turn on the light. Right. So that of course would not
be. And that's exactly the point. Okay. So that's exactly why the
normal rule is you go by your state of mind at the
time. The חידוש *chiddush* of תמורה temurah *Temurah*
is that we—you—it's that you're held responsible, at least according to this.
Right. But that's exactly what I see, that what this opinion is
trying to do. If it's about lashes, so troubling that you get
lashes when you're unintentional, that at least he wants to limit it
to a case where at least you expressed your desire and intent
before, so it can then frame the act afterwards. Now again, how
long afterwards? Two days afterwards or two minutes afterwards? The sense one
gets is more like two minutes, not two days, but who knows?
Now that's the way רש"י *Rashi* reads it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* reads
it that you're actually making a תנאי tnai *tnai*. You say, not
that you're going to do an act, you say, "When I enter
into this house, then this animal
should be—it's like a תנאי tnai? *tnai*—then this animal should be an
exchange for the other, or this animal should be sanctified when I
enter into this house." And then when you walked into the house,
you
had totally forgotten your condition and you were just going in to
get a drink of water. So when the actual תמורה temurah *Temurah*
or קדושה kedusha *kedushah* took effect, you're, you know, you were not
willing it to take effect at the time. You'd only stipulated it
before. Okay. Now so that again, why that should matter in terms
of the effect, that doesn't make sense. Right? If I made a
תנאי this will take effect and the תנאי in this condition, the
condition was satisfied, so the act takes effect. So why would we
say by normal things that the thing would not become קדוש kadosh.
just because I wasn't thinking about it at the time of the
תנאי? So again, that type of way of reading the גמרא Gemara
makes more sense if the issue is about getting lashes and it's
about the willful nature rather than if it's about the issue about
taking effect. Okay, so we have two different ways to read the
cases. It makes sense that some of the cases are more talking
and read that actually this debate of the two בעלי התוספות Ba'alei
HaTosafot is really a debate I would say of the אמוראים. Amoraim.
How do you read the statement of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi
Yosei Berabbi Yehuda? Is it about the lashes or is it about
taking effect? If it's about lashes, so then it's a tremendous חידוש
to get lashes for תמורה temurah, for שוגג. The contrast is to
קדשים that you don't normally get lashes for sanctifying but trying to
sanctify a בעל מום. ba'al mum, Okay, but then there's somehow that
תמורה temurah you would get lashes in more cases even in not
fully willful cases. If it's about taking effect, then the reason תמורה
temurah takes effect in more cases, even cases of טעות and of
error, is because you're not creating the קדושה kedusha from scratch, you're
transferring it from existing תמורה, temurah so it's easier for it to
transfer once it already exists. Yes. When a person entered the house,
he forgot what he had said outside. Yes. So how does it
come about that it would even take effect? Well, if you basically
said, 'This will take effect when I walk into the house,' and
then, yeah, even without witnesses it happened, whether we can prove it
or whatever is a different question, but once the condition is met,
the condition is met, whether you were willing it at the time
or not. So he'd have to remember at some point what he
said. Oh, yes. Oh, I see your point. Yes, yes. Afterwards people
reminded him about, 'Hey, didn't you say...' and he said, 'Oh my
gosh, I forgot.' All right, so, yes. There's something I find troubling.
Someone, lashes is not a small thing. Right? It can almost kill
someone. Terrible pain. Right. That someone should get lashes, that actually that
this could happen, right, to think for wanting to give something to
God, whether it's changing one animal for the other, whatever, but the
entire intention was a religious one. Right. And nobody was harmed, there
was nothing actually happened in the real world. Right. And for thinking
something that a government or whatever, theocracy can come and harm someone
almost to the point of killing them because they thought the wrong
thing, which affected nobody. Well, it's not just that they thought, they
acted. But it didn't affect, it's not even like being like Charlie's
example from the חילול שבת, chillul Shabbat, so everyone's שבת is a
little diminished. This is an internal thing. Well, again, it's not internal,
you said something, but look, I think, okay, I hear the point
and I do think that the problem, there's two questions that you're
implicitly asking. One is getting lashes for תמורה temurah. altogether. The other
is then even extending it to cases of שוגג. So I would
say extending it to cases of שוגג, first of all, you know,
the גמרא Gemara pulls back from that and tries to limit it
more and more, and in the תוספות you have those that try
to deny that anybody ever said that you get lashes for שוגג.
Okay, so that's that question. In terms of the general question of
why do you get lashes for something that is purely a sort
of religious sin and not hurting anybody? I mean, that's just a
very, sort of contemporary, sort of more secular mindset that the problem
is crime more than sin. I mean, the תורה clearly has, you
know, very weighty punishments for things that just are sins to God
without affecting society. Now you can try to reframe them as not...
Right, so that's the point. It's not just that it doesn't hurt
anybody, it's that you are trying to do a good thing. Right.
You're so... I very much hear you. So if I bring a
קרבן korban on a במה bamah with good intention, do I get
lashes? Well, yes. So, yeah, that's a good contrast. Right. So, so
that's a good point, which is yes, that within that realm, yes,
even like, you know, so much we're going to be reading and
we're starting to read about, you know, the כהנים Kohanim and their
role to protect the temple and והזר הקרב יומת. vehazar hakarev yummat.
So part of, you know, it's a bigger question, but part of
the whole issue is that yes, you know, even when you're working
within the religious sphere, you have to be very careful to do
things correctly. So we'll just acknowledge that issue right now. So let's
go on. All right, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says רבי אלעזר ורבי יוחנן בתרפות. Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Yochanan bitreifot. So
now we get to the question about כלאים kilayim and טרפה, treifah,
which are things that are even worse than a בעל מום, ba'al
mum, that תמורה temurah. does not take effect on them. Let's take
a look. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, לא קדושים בתמורה ולא מקדישים. lo
kedoshim bitmurah velo makdishim. They do not become sanctified if you try
to do תמורה, temurah they don't become תמורה. temurah So, but, and
so even though normally by תמורה temurah, something gets a קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, these are so much worse than a normal בעל מום
ba'al mum. that they don't even that they do not get affected
by תמורה, temurah they do not get a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
Now what does it really, now the question is do they get
even do they get some type of קדושת דמים? kedushat damim? And
the answer is probably not. It says not at all. And the
reason is because by תמורה temurah, if you can't say והיה הוא
ותמורתו יהיה קדש, vehayah hu utmurato yihyeh kodesh, if you can't say
the thing gets the same קדושה kedusha as... original, then it's like
trying to do תמורה temurah. on a, you know, on a car.
Right? If I sanctified a car, it has קדושת דמים, kedushat damim,
but if I tried to do תמורה temurah on a car, then
it doesn't have any קדושה, kedusha so they don't become קדוש kadosh
at all, ולא מקדישים velo makdishim and if they are קדוש, kadosh,
they cannot be לעשות תמורה, la'asot temurah, you cannot use them as
the source to make something a תמורה temurah because you can only
make תמורה temurah from something that has קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. So
תניא, tanya, so there's an obvious question here which we looked at
before and we're going to do it again. אמר רבי מאיר, amar
Rabbi Meir, ומאחר שאין קדושים מהיכן מקדישים? ume'achar she'ein kedoshim meheichan makdishim?
So if you cannot become sanctified, how can you ever be a
source of sanctity? How could I think to use them as the
basis for תמורה? temurah Meaning, number one, if you did תמורה temurah.
they wouldn't become קדוש. kadosh Number two is, if I tried to
sanctify them directly, it's certainly as bad as trying to sanctify a
בעל מום ba'al mum and it only has קדושת דמים, kedushat damim,
not קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, it doesn't have the intrinsic קרבן korban
קדושה. kedusha, So you cannot do תמורה tmura, without something that has
קרבן korban קדושה. kedusha. How did this get it? Not through תמורה,
tmura, not through הקדשה, hakdasha, how did it get it? Okay, so
אלא אי אתה מוצא אלא, ela ee ata motzei ela, here are
how you're going to have some of these scenarios. במקדיש בהמה ועשתה
טריפה, bemakdish behemah ve'astah tereifah, the טריפה tereifah case is first you
gave it קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf then it became a טריפה, tereifah,
so it retains the קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf and therefore I could
have thought, let's remember, I could have thought that it would be
the source of תמורה tmura? because it does have קדושת הגוף. kedushat
haguf. Part of these exclusions are even when they have קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf in the special cases we're about to say, because they
are so, you know, different, worse than a בעל מום, ba'al mum,
they can't even be the source of תמורה tmura, even when they
do have, when you do find a case where they have קדושת
הגוף. kedushat haguf. Or even tried to intentionally do תמורה tmura, on
that, then it, then nothing at all. Correct. As opposed to the
other case where they would have to שוגג and get מלקות. malkot.
Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so במקדיש ולד
ויצא דרך דופן, bemakdish velad veyatza derech dofen, or I sanctified a
fetus and it came out through C-section. I sanctified a fetus, it
had קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, right? Because at that time it was
not yet a C-section baby, and now it came out by a
C-section, so now it has the problem after it had קדושת הגוף.
kedushat haguf. So I might think you could do תמורה. tmura No,
once it has these problems, even if it has קדושת הגוף, kedushat
haguf, you can't, it was not the basis of תמורה. tmura, אבל,
aval, but how, those work, those you can sanctify before the problem
comes about. אבל כלאים וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס, aval kilayim vetumtum ve'androgynos, crossbreed and
these mixed gender or uncertain gender, those are things that it starts
its life that way. And how do you, so if you say
you can't sanctify it in utero, it's still כלאים kilayim in utero,
it's still or it's still a טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum ve'androgynos in utero,
right? So you can't work that around by sanctifying it in utero.
So אי אתה מוצא אלא בוולדי קדשים. ee ata motzei ela bevladay
kodashim. But what you could do is sanctify the mother. If I
tried to sanctify the animal directly, if, oh you know, sanctifying a
כלאים, kilayim, you're sanctifying a טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum ve'androgynos, it never gets
קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. But if I sanctify the mother and then
let's say then it becomes pregnant, then the קדושה kedusha that affects
the child is derived from the mother. So since the mother has
קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, the child also gets קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
even though the child has these issues. Okay, so you can't do
it directly since it already has the issues and it's אין מקדישים,
ein makdishim, it will never have קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, but it
can derive the קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf from the mother. אלא אי
אתה מוצא אלא במקדיש, אב, סורי, אלא בוולדי קדשים. ela ee ata
motzei ela bemakdish, ab, sorry, ela bevladay kodashim. Now, within that, it's
אליבא דרבי יהודה, aliba deRabbi Yehuda, it would only be a relevant
point according to Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר הוולדות עושים תמורה, de'amar havladot osim
temurah, because normally there's an opinion that you cannot do תמורה tmura
from a, from something that has derivative קדושה kedusha anyway, from an
offspring of a קרבן. korban. But Rabbi Yehuda says you can. So
assuming that normally you would be able to do תמורה tmura, from
an offspring of a קרבן, korban, here you can't because it also
is כלאים וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס, kilayim vetumtum ve'androgynos, okay? So basically what are
we saying? It's not the object of תמורה, tmura although תמורה tmura
takes effect on a בעל מום, ba'al mum it doesn't affect on
this. And if you have a special scenario in which these things
got קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, which is very hard because they're not
the object of תמורה, tmura if I tried to sanctify it's only
קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, but in the special scenarios we just described
that they got קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, they are not the, then
they still can't be used in the, in the act of תמורה.
tmura, If you tried to do תמורה tmura with them, it will
not succeed. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, now, okay.
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, now we finally get around to
asking what makes these worse than a בעל מום. ba'al mum מאי
טעמא דרבי אלעזר? mai ta'ama deRabbi Elazar? What's the reason of Rabbi
Elazar? So כבהמה טמאה, kebehemah teme'ah, because he compares these to like
a completely non-kosher animal. מה בהמה טמאה, mah behemah teme'ah, like if
you tried to do תמורה tmura on a camel. So מה טמאה
לא קרבה ולא נחתי לה קדושת הגוף, mah teme'ah lo karvah velo
nachteih lah kedushat haguf, the same way those things you can't bring
as a קרבן, korban, a camel, and if you tried to sanctify
it or you tried to do תמורה tmura it would never get
קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, it would never get intrinsic sanctity, אף הנך
לא קרבי ולא נחתו קדושת הגוף, af hanach lo karvi velo natchu
kedushat haguf, so these too because they can't be brought as a
קרבן, korban, they're therefore categorically excluded, can't be used as תמורה tmura
and will never get a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf if you try
to sanctify them, well anyway, they certainly cannot be the object of
תמורה. tmura Now that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to obviously
ask. Okay. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא, amar leih Rav Pappa leRava,
so Rav Pappa says to Rava, והרי בעל מום, veharei ba'al mum,
what do you mean? You're, oh these are different categories. What makes
you think these are categorically in a, you know, in a categorically
different category than בעל מום ba'al mum *baal mum*? So here's his
answer. בעל מום ba'al mum קרב במינו *baal mum karev b'mino*. No,
בעל מום ba'al mum. *baal mum* you have other similar animals, it's
just got its problem, but animals of this genre, if you would,
of this category normally are brought. Here, they're basically a different category
of animal. Now, what do you mean it's a different category of
animal? Meaning טומטום Tumtum *tumtum* ואנדרוגינוס *v'androgynous*, why we understand you'd call
it a different category, although טומטום tumtum, *tumtum* ואנדרוגינוס *v'androgynous* they're still
sheep, but nevertheless you could sort of say, you know, that the,
you know, that they're a different gender and that places them in
a different category. But יוצא דופן yotzei dofen. *yotzei dofen*, טריפה treifa,
*treifa*, those aren't a different category, that's a sheep with a, with
something different that happened to it. So how can you say that
that puts it in a different category? So that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to ask. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says, אי הכי טריפה treifa נמי
כקבר במינה *i hachi treifa nami kakavar b'mina*, how about טריפה treifa
*treifa*? It doesn't have יוצא דופן yotzei dofen, *yotzei dofen* also mentioned,
talk to that in a minute. אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava,
*ela amar Rava*, alright you're right, fine, so it's not that it's
a different category. אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava, *ela amar Rava*,
כבהמה טמאה ke'behema tmeia, *k'behema t'meia*, here's why it's like a בהמה
טמאה behema tmeia. *behema t'meia*. מה בהמה טמאה פסולה גוף אף גב
פסולה גוף *ma behema t'meia psula guf af go psula guf*. The
same way as a non-kosher animal is a, is a, is a
problem of its identity, a פסולה גוף *psula guf*, an intrinsic problem,
even everything else which is an intrinsic problem. And how is בעל
מום ba'al mum, *baal mum* different? לאפוקי בעל מום ba'al mum דפסולי
חסרון נינהו *l'apukei baal mum d'psulei chisaron inu*. A בעל מום ba'al
mum *baal mum* is not somehow an intrinsic problem, it's a problem
of lacking. Now what exactly does that mean? Well, it's interesting conceptually
to see the way the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* understands it in a
מר *mar*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't understand it that what it
means is that a בעל מום ba'al mum? *baal mum* is that
there's something physically missing from the animal, like doesn't have a limb.
And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to challenge, what do
you mean? You can have a מום mum *mum* when it has
something extra, or when it has like fused, you know, fused, what
do you call those, hooves or something. Okay, so let's just read
that question and then I'll go back to this. It says, אמר
ליה רב אדא לרבא *amar lei Rav Ada l'Rava*, ולא שרוע וקלוט
כתיב בפרשה *v'lo sarua v'kalut ktiv b'parsha*, how about fused hooves? So
that's not lacking anything. והני פסולי גוף נינהו *v'hani psulei guf ninhu*,
and those are not a, it's not a lacking, it's just a
problem that the body is somehow different. So you can't say the
issue is lacking versus non-lacking. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* translated רבא
Rava *Rava*'s very literally, that the idea was that something was lacking,
and that in the other cases, like it could be a טריפה
treifa. *treifa* without lacking, you have a hole in your lung even
if no skin is lacking, that's a טריפה treifa, *treifa*, you know,
the mixed gender, the כלאים kilayim, *kilayim*, the יוצא דופן yotzei dofen
*yotzei dofen*, something was lacking. Okay, but again, what I would sort
of say that conceptually it wasn't like there was a, in defense
of רבא Rava *Rava* here, it wasn't so much whether it was
a physical thing that was lacking and because sometimes you can have
a בעל מום ba'al mum. *baal mum* that isn't physically lacking and
undershot his position, but it's really a question of conceptually how do
we feel it. You know, בעל מום ba'al mum. *baal mum* is
just, is more like, in some types of a thing, you, I'm
trying to think about the way to say this, meaning, but part
of the whole problem here is because I got to share, you
know, I think I've shared this with you before, you know, the
whole issue about בעל מום ba'al mum *baal mum* and the whole
focus on like perfection and so on, you know, I mean, so
it's one thing in the context of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*
and so on, we just read פסוקים *psukim* in the פרשה *parsha*
about the כהנים *Kohanim* and the way they dress, so you certainly
understand that you want a very particular type of aesthetics and experience
in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, both for the כהנים *Kohanim* and
the קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* and so on. But translating it elsewhere can
be, you know, very problematic because, you know, people shouldn't be judged
by those types of things and concepts of perfection and so on.
And I'm speaking from a position of somebody who has two kids
that have special needs and the idea of a society's concepts of
perfection and so on is very challenging. And I think one way
you could read what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is talking about here
is about to what degree do we label something as like different
or do we label, you know, you're different and you're other, and
to what degree do we label something as just like, well, you
know, you just don't have this ability. You know, he doesn't have
the ability to do a higher level, you know, whatever, you know,
whatever, like a processing or something like that. It frames it very
differently to say, you know, this person lacks this certain type of
ability than to say, yeah, this person's like totally weird and different.
Okay, so I think that I have a sense that like, you
know, that that's a little bit what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying, that a בעל מום ba'al mum, *baal mum* you could understand,
okay, you're not exactly perfect, you know, you're lacking a little something,
you know, you don't have exactly this quality that other things have.
Whereas, you know, these other types of things, now again, that saves
the בעל מום mum. *baal mum* category and makes the negative connotation
in the others, but you understand where it's coming from, that these
other types of things, possibly, you know, יוצא דופן yotzei dofen? *yotzei
dofen*, certainly the case of כלאים *kilayim*, the mixed gender, which also
then becomes insensitive to people with mixed gender issues or, you know,
etc. whatsoever. But anyway, I think that's more where רבא *Rava* is
going, trying to say conceptually, not physically, lacking versus not lacking, but
conceptually are we just labeling this as different? and other, or we
labeling this as something is, something here is not exactly the way
it is by everything else. Anyway, that's my little defense of רבא
and me getting on my soapbox. But okay. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't like it. Is there overlap between מום mum and טרפה?
treifa? No, not really. I mean, they're, if it's a serious מום,
mum but a lot of מומים mumim are completely aesthetic. A מום
mum. is if you had to remove a leg of an animal?
Yes, you could, you could, you could. Okay, so anyway, so now
the גמרא Gemara says, by the way, by the way, when the
גמרא Gemara. just tries to say it was categorically different, when the
גמרא Gemara tries to just say it was categorically different, it's interesting
that it only asks the challenge from טרפה treifa and not from
יוצא דופן. And what רש"י says is, well, יוצא דופן, that was
so bizarre, of course, C-sections are very common, although even too common,
but that's another discussion, another soapbox. But anyway, but רש"י was so
bizarre, right, I mean, obviously by like מדבש, midvash, right, not a
woman born, I mean, a C-section was like so bizarre that it
puts in people's minds an animal or a person that was born
by C-section in a completely different category. So the only one that
is sort of seen as not categorically different is טרפה. treifa. But
the גמרא at least challenged it based on that. So we still
don't know why these things are treated completely differently. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא says like this, okay, so the גמרא
says like this, where are we? אלא אמר רבא, I think. אלא
אמר רבא, כבהמה טמאה, thank you. So rather רבא says like a
בהמה טמאה. מה בהמה טמאה ליתא במינה, אף כל דליתא במינה. Ma
behema tmeia leita be'mina, af kol deleita be'mina. So we're going back
to that answer, that it's a completely different category. Non-kosher animals is
a different category, these are non-kosher animals are a different category. לאפוקי
בעל מום דאיתא במינה Le'apukei ba'al mum de'ita be'mina as opposed to
a בעל מום mum that it's basically the same type of animal,
it just happens to have a מום. mum. So now what was
our question? מאי אמרת טרפה איתא במינה? Mai amart treifa ita be'mina?
You said that an animal with that's a טרפה, treifa, like a
hole in the lung or something, that's not a different category, it's
just an animal with, it's still a sheep, it's just a טרפה.
treifa. לא דמי לבעל מום. Lo dami le'ba'al mum. You're right, it's
not a different category, but there's another reason why it is more
excluded. Why? בהמה טמאה אסורה באכילה, וטרפה אסורה באכילה, לאפוקי בעל מום
דמותר באכילה. Behema tmeia asura ba'achila, ve'treifa asura ba'achila, le'apukei ba'al mum
de'mutar ba'achila. No, it's different for another way. You're right, it's not
categorically different in the way we described before, but it's also a
separate reason for exclusion. It's excluded because it can't be eaten. That's
not, and therefore it's just like a non-kosher animal that can't be
eaten. So what רבא is saying is like this: these group of
things that are considered different than a בעל מום, mum they're different
than a בעל מום mum. for one of two reasons. Either they're
different from a בעל מום mum. because conceptually we just think them,
put them in this completely different category, this other category, including the,
so some of them are obvious why we would do that, or
where or why people do that, which isn't making a value judgment.
And the other, and the case about יוצא דופן we already described,
in people's minds it's just othered. So those things are seen as
a completely different מין, min, a completely different type of thing. And
the טרפה treifa is not like a בעל מום mum for a
different reason. It's worse than a בעל מום mum because it can't
be eaten. And since it can't be eaten, that also means that
it's treated differently and not just like a בעל מום. mum, Okay,
so now that's why these are all treated differently. Okay, אמר שמואל.
Amar Shmuel. Now we're going to have שמואל's Shmuel's statement, which is
going to be a little shocking, seems to go against everything we
said, and that the גמרא we will basically reject שמואל. Shmuel. But
let's take a look. אמר שמואל המקדיש את הטרפה צריכה מום קבוע
לפדותה עליו. Amar Shmuel hamakdish et hatreifa tzricha mum kavua lifdota alav.
If you sanctify a טרפה, treifa, you need another blemish in order
to redeem it, which means that if you sanctify a טרפה, treifa,
it gets קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Now you can only redeem something
with a blemish. So a טרפה treifa is a טרפה, treifa, but
it's not a blemish, it's an internal, you need an external. You
need the external blemish. So a מום mum, is an external blemish.
Now that's, so there's a certain logic to that, but the problem
is all along what we've been saying is if you're מקדיש makdish
a בעל מום, mum it never gets קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, and
we're saying these things are worse than a בעל מום and they
can't even be the object of a תמורה, tmura. which means they
can't even get קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf even when קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf should force its way in. And how here you're saying it
actually can get קדושת הגוף? kedushat haguf? Well, what do you do
with our משנה? Mishna? How can you say such a thing? So
maybe he's saying because רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said it and maybe
they disagree. Yeah, so that's, right, so it could be he's disagreeing,
but again, to say that it's רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, anyway, yes,
it's fine. So let's take a look. שמע מינה פודים את הקדשים
להאכילן לכלבים? Shma mina podin et hakodashim le'ha'achilan laklavim? The גמרא's first
question is otherwise. שמע מינה פודים את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים? Shma mina
podin et hakodashim le'ha'achilan laklavim? First of all, how can, forget before
we get to attacking it the base of it, how can you
redeem such an animal? What are you going to do with this
animal if you redeem it? It's a טרפה. treifa. So what are
you going to do with it? You're going to have to שחט
shecht it and use it as dog food. So since when are
you allowed to redeem sacrifices if you're not going to eat them,
if they're just going to be able to, you turn them into
dog food? So there's actually a מחלוקת in the גמרא. We're assuming
אין פודים את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. ein podin et hakodashim le'ha'achilan laklavim.
...even if I accept your point that it gets קדושת הגוף, kedushas
haguf, since when are you allowed to redeem it in those cases?
So the גמרא says fine. אלא אימא עושה קדושה למות. Ela eima
ose kedusha lamus. Okay, there's Rivka's favorite case. Okay, you're right. It
gets קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. You're not allowed to redeem it because
אין פודין את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. ein podin es hakodashim l'ha'achilam l'klavim.
And now what do you do with it? You can't bring it
as a קרבן. korban. You can't redeem it. You have to let
it die. So sanctity caused it to die. Yes. Yes. But I
mean you don't let it just graze and live out the rest
of its days? Oh, you could probably let it do that except
that there would be a problem about, you know, תקלה takala and
misusing it. It's not like the case of חטאת מתה chatas mesa
which is a more sort of active thing. Okay, now רב אושעיא
אמר Rav Oshaya amar and רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaya says אינה אלא
כמי שמקדיש עצים ואבנים בבעלי מומין. eina ela k'makdish eitzim v'avanim b'ba'alei
mumin. So give me a break, right? It's like trying to be
מקדיש Makdish something with a מום and this is worse than a
מום. It's like trying to be מקדיש wood and therefore it gets
קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. It doesn't have קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. If
it has קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, then you can remove the קדושת
דמים. kedushas damim. You don't have to treat it like all of
the ideas of requiring a blemish for redeeming and all of those
issues. Okay, fine. תנן. Tnan. Now let's going to try to prove
it. כל הקדשים שנעשו טרפה אין פודים אותם לפי שאין פודים את
הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. Kol hakodashim shena'asu treifa ein podim osam l'fi she'ein
podim es hakodashim l'ha'achilam l'klavim. Here's a משנה. Mishna. If a קרבן
korban you sanctified an animal and then it became a טריפה, treifa,
you're not allowed to redeem it because you can't redeem a קרבנות
korbanos, just to make them into dog food. So the גמרא says
טעמא שנעשו. taima shena'asu. The scenario is that they became a טריפה
treifa after they were sanctified. הא היו מעיקרא. Ha hayu mei'ikara. If
it was a טריפה treifa before you sanctified it, פודים אותם. podim
osam. You could redeem it or, you know, because it would never
have gotten קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. It would never have been a
קרבן. korban. So the גמרא says no. דילמא האי תנא סבר לה
כל היכא דלא חזי לגופא לא נחתא ליה קדושת הגוף. Dilma hai
tanna savar lah kol heicha d'lo chazi l'gufa lo nachsa lei kedushas
haguf. Okay, maybe this תנא tanna disagrees with שמואל. Shmuel. This תנא
tanna is of the opinion that if it can't be used, then
it doesn't get קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. But I don't hold that
way. Now what does he mean? Since when can you say you
don't hold like a תנא? tanna? So implicitly what's being said here
is what Michael said in the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes that actually
switches the גרסא, which is I don't agree with רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer of the משנה. Mishna. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was one opinion.
He said that these things are categorically excluded. I don't agree with
him and I actually think that if it's got these issues, you
can sanctify them. Okay, that was just רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer opinion
and I think you can sanctify them. Do you say the same
for the other ones too? Yeah, presumably. Yeah. תא שמע. Ta shema.
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer and here's the רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer of the משנה. Mishna. הכלאים והטרפה והיוצא דופן והטומטום והאנדרוגינוס לא
קדושים ולא מקדישים. Hakilayim v'hatreifa v'hayotzei dofen v'hatumtum v'ha'androgynos lo kedoshim v'lo
makdishim. ואמר שמואל, V'amar Shmuel, you שמואל Shmuel yourself explain רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer to say לא קדושים בתמורה ולא מקדישים לעשות תמורה, lo
kedoshim b'tmura v'lo makdishim la'asos tmura, that they cannot be the source
of they cannot become קדוש kadosh. through תמורה, tmura they can't be
the source of it. Now lest you were to think that it
means that somehow if you were to sanctify it directly it could
work, then we know that's not true either. דתניא, Detanya, אמר רבי
מאיר, amar Rabbi Meir, וכי מאחר שאינן קדושים היאך מקדישים? v'chi mei'achar
she'einan kedoshim heich makdishim? If they can never become קדוש, kadosh. how
did you ever get into the discussion of whether they can be
the source of תמורה? tmura So it's implicit here that they can
never become קדוש kadosh except in the very special cases we figured
out earlier in the גמרא. So you שמואל Shmuel says you can
make them קדוש. kadosh, It's clear here you can't make them קדוש.
kadosh? So the גמרא says אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela ei
itmar hachi itmar, אלא במקדיש בהמה ואחר כך נטרפה, ela b'makdish behema
v'achar kach nitrefa, etc., etc. So those are the special cases. It
had to first sanctified and then it became a טריפה. treifa The
גמרא says it's very clear according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir what?
האי טרפה מעיקרא. Hai treifa mei'ikara. If it started off as a
טריפה, לא נחתא לה קדושת הגוף. lo nachsa lah kedushas haguf. There's
no way you can give it קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. And how
can you שמואל Shmuel say otherwise? So the גמרא says אמר לך
שמואל. amar lach Shmuel. He'll say back to you what he said
a minute ago. דילמא האי תנא או האי תנא סבר לה כל
היכא דלא חזי לגופא לא נחתא ליה קדושת הגוף. Dilma hai tanna
o hai tanna savar lah kol heicha d'lo chazi l'gufa lo nachsa
lei kedushas haguf. Yeah, good. That's what that תנא tanna holds. That's
what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir hold. But
they are one opinion and presumably there's another opinion out there. Now
is שמואל Shmuel saying that you can be מקדיש an animal with
a מום and give it קדושת הגוף? kedushas haguf? That seems impossible.
א he would have said it. ב there are explicit משניות that
make it extremely clear that, you know, it's one thing to be
מקדיש an animal and then get a מום. מקדיש an animal with
a מום is very different and that type of thing can never
get קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. It seems what שמואל Shmuel is saying
is like the opposite take of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is saying that this group of things I mentioned, טריפה,
כלאים, etc., are so different from קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf they're categorically
excluded, they'll never even get קדושה, kedusha you know, even by תמורה,
tmura? etc. They're so worse. What שמואל Shmuel is saying is no,
no, they're not worse. In a way they're better. If you would,
they're problems but they're some of the cases they're invisible problems. טומטום
and אנדרוגינוס androgynos not exactly, but anyway, they're problems but they're not
the aesthetic problems of מום. So therefore, yes, there's a הלכה halacha
they can't be offered up as a קרבן. korban. That's true. But
that doesn't mean they're as bad as מום. And therefore, because at
least aesthetically they look the same, if you sanctify them they get
a קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. It's just a הלכה halacha that you
can't bring them as a קרבן. korban. But that doesn't it doesn't
exclude them the way a מום would, which is why which is
why you might say this ironic thing: you can't bring it as
a קרבן, korban, but you can't yet redeem it worse than a
מום and will never get קדושה like the first opinion that we
saw? Or do you say it's better? It's basically in the category
more, it's just a הלכה halacha you can't bring it yet and
actually can get a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf and the only way
that you can redeem it is once it actually gets that very
visible מום, that pushes it off enough to allow you to redeem
it. Yes, Charles. So the problem with טריפה is it's a lot
of times you don't know if an animal's טריפה until after you've
actually שחט shacht it. Right. So a lot of times you would
be sanctifying a טריפה בשוגג. beshogeg. Yeah, right. Okay. But then you're
an אונס oness and that's also an interesting question that might be
the debate here, although I don't know. Within the prohibition of לאו
of sanctifying an animal with a מום, would you include an animal
that is a טומטום, אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, or יוצא דופן? So here you
actually have, right, and it could be both שמואל Shmuel and רבי
אליעזר Rav Eliezer would say no. You know, for either reason, one
is it's close enough you didn't do something so bad, or it's
so far away it was irrelevant what you did. Okay, but anyway,
but that is an interesting point. If that's true, you'd be an
אונס, oness, but exactly, you know, that's part of this debate. How
do you view these types of animals? You know, closer to being
a קרבן korban or further away from being a קרבן? korban? These
animals have to be the, you know, the minor ones with the
hole in the lung versus like if it was missing a leg.
Yeah, right, right, right. Then it's already a מום and absolutely. Okay,
let's start הדרן עלך כל הקרבנות, Hadran alach kol ha-korbanos, we don't
have too much time, but let's try to get a little bit
into now the next פרק. perek. אלו קדשים שולדותיהן ותמורותיהן כיוצא בהן.
Elu kodshim she-vladosem ve-tmurosem ke-yotzei ba-hen. The following animals, their offspring have
the same הלכה halacha and their תמורה, tmura they get the קדושה
from the parent if you would, or from the original, and their
status is the same as the original, they can even be brought
as a קרבן. korban. Which is not necessarily the same type of
קרבן, korban, right? Well, we'll see. For שלמים, shelamim yes, for the
first ones, yes. So the basic הלכה halacha is that the תמורה
tmura, becomes קדוש kadosh? and is so קדוש, and this is the
general rule, that it's even brought as a קרבן. korban. Not for
חטאת, chatas, but the general rule is that it's even brought as
a קרבן. korban. Okay, so let's take a look. Here are the
animals that their children and their תמורה, tmura we'll start with the
שלמים. shelamim, ולד שלמים ותמורתן, Vlad shelamim ve-tmurosan, a child of a
שלמים shelamim, because you can have it, a שלמים shelamim. can be
females, or a תמורה tmura, of a שלמים, shlamim. ולדן ולדן ולד
ולדן עד סוף כל העולם. vladan vladan vlad vladan ad sof kol
ha-olam. Their children, grandchildren until the end of the world, הרי הן
שלמים, harei hen shelamim, they are all שלמים. Okay, וטעונים סמיכה ונסכים
ותנופת חזה ושוק. u-te'unim semicha ve-nesachim ve-tenufat chazeh ve-shok. And you treat
them fully like שלמים. Okay, you do סמיכה, semicha, you bring the
wine and the flour, you wave the חזה chazeh and the שוק,
shok, the breast and the thigh. You give them the full treatment
of שלמים, they are 100% קדושת שלמים, kedushas shelamim, whether it's a
תמורה, whether it is a child. Now, you can't say תמורת תמורתן
tmuras tmurosan because the הלכה halacha is אין תמורה עושה תמורה. ein
tmura osa tmura. So that's the one way a תמורה would not
be exactly like it, that it can't daisy chain. But the children,
ולד וולדי ולדן עד סוף כל העולם. vlad ve-vladei vladan ad sof
kol ha-olam. Let's take a look at the גמרא. כיון דתניא ולדן
וולדי ולדן עד סוף כל העולם למה לי? Keivan de-tanya vladan ve-vladei
vladan ad sof kol ha-olam lamma li? So since you said their
children and grandchildren, why do you have to say till the end
of time? Isn't that obvious? No, it's not so obvious. תניא דנן
שמע ליה לרבי אליעזר דאמר ולד שלמים לא יקרב שלמים. Tanya de-nan
shema lei le-Rabbi Eliezer de-amar vlad shelamim lo yikrav shelamim. In the
next משנה mishnah there's going to be רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who
says no, actually a child of a שלמים cannot be brought. It's
not the same as the mother. ואמרי ליה תנא דידן, Ve-amrei lei
tanna didan, so our תנא tanna is saying back very strongly, לא
מיבעיא ולדן, lo mibaya vladan, not only do I disagree with you
about the children, דלא מודינא לך, de-lo modina lach, and I say
that that's close enough to be a שלמים, אלא אפילו עד סוף
כל העולם לא מודינא לך. ella afilu ad sof kol ha-olam lo
modina lach. To the point you wouldn't go so far to exaggerate
this if you weren't arguing with someone, is what the גמרא is
saying. But because it's arguing, they're saying listen, even עד סוף כל
העולם. ad sof kol ha-olam. Of course you know you understand that
because with copy machines, right, you always know second and third and
fourth generation copies are always less and less like the original. So
here it says doesn't matter, עד סוף כל העולם. ad sof kol
ha-olam. Okay, let's go a little bit more. מנא הני מילי? Mana
hani mili? Where do we know this from? That this idea that
you can bring a תמורה as a קרבן? korban? תנו רבנן. Tanu
rabbanan. So this is the first question, how do you know you
can bring a תמורה as a קרבן? korban? Okay, זכר. zachar. It
says, or how do you know you can bring a ולד vlad
as a קרבן? korban? Excuse me. So it says this is by
a שלמים, it says אם זכר אם נקבה, im zachar im nekeiva,
if it's male or female. So it says why did it have
to say if it's male or female? Don't say anything and I'll
know it could be male or female. So why is it saying
it? זכר, zachar, male, לרבות את הולד, le-rabos es ha-vlad, even a
child can be brought. ולא דין הוא? Ve-lo din hu? I would
have thought no, don't bring a child, an offspring of a שלמים.
ומה תמורה שאין גידולי הקדש קריבה. U-mah tmura she-ein gidulei hekdesh kreiva.
I'm sorry, why do I need a פסוק? pasuk? I could have
obviously learned it out from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If תמורה,
which I'm about to show in a minute, even though it's not,
it was not grown in a קרבן, korban, it was not gestated
in a קרבן, korban, can be brought as a קרבן, korban, ולד
שגידולי הקדש, vlad she-gidulei hekdesh, so a ולד vlad that actually comes
from a קרבן, korban, אינו דין שיקרב? eino din she-yikarev? Certainly it
should be brought. Why do I need a פסוק? No, מה לתמורה
שכן היא הקדש בכל הקדשים. mah le-tmura she-kein hi hekdesh be-chol ha-kodshim.
So, no, תמורה applies by all animals. ולד vlad can only happen
by female קרבנות, korbanos, which is not all קרבנות, not an עולה,
not an אשם. asham. So maybe I would think אינו קרב. eino
karev. הואיל ואינו נוהג בכל הקדשים, ho'il ve-eino noheg be-chol ha-kodshim, maybe
that would be a reason to say you can't bring it. תלמוד
לומר זכר לרבות את הולד. Talmud lomar zachar le-rabos es ha-vlad. So
the extra word comes to tell me the child of a קרבן
korban can, from the word זכר, zachar, a little ironically, we'll get
back to that irony in a minute. נקבה, nekeiva, קודש יקדש, kodesh
yekadash, it doesn't tell me whether that's enough קדושה to bring it
as a קרבן. korban. So we learn that out here from the
word נקבה. nekeyvah. אין לי אלא תמורה תמימה, ein li ela tmura
temima, ולד תמימים. vlad temimim. I only know if it's the תמורה
of an animal without a blemish that itself could be brought as
a קרבן. korban. ולד תמימים, vlad temimim, ולד בעלי מומין, vlad ba'alei
mumin, or the ולד vlad of a תמים tamim or the child
of an animal without a blemish. ולד בעלי מומין, vlad ba'alei mumin,
תמורת בעלי מומין מנין? tmuras ba'alei mumin minayin? How do I know
even if it's the תמורה of a בעל מום or the child
of a בעל מום? Maybe if it's derived from the קדושה from
the mother, then the mother's קדושה is not fit to be brought
as a קרבן. korban. It's interesting how do you see an animal
with a blemish? You say the קדושה is the קדושה to be
brought as a קרבן, korban, the blemish is getting in the way,
or maybe the presence of the blemish, you know, redefines the קדושה,
changes the קדושה. This seems to assume the latter. Once the mother
or the original animal has a blemish, its קדושה is not קדושת
מזבח kedushas mizbeach to be brought. It's קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach but
not to allow it to be brought. So the child or the
תמורה should also not be able to be brought. It shouldn't have
more קדושה than the mother. מנין, minayin, how do you know that
even they become קדוש? Or well, we'll see how much not true
it is in a minute. Anyway, but how do you know at
least that they become קדוש? תלמוד לומר אם זכר. Talmud lomar im
zachar. The extra אם im is extra because it could have just
taken out the whole phrase. This is by שלמים. לרבות ולדי בעלי
מומין, le-rabos vladei ba'alei mumin, even the child of a בעל מום.
אם נקבה, im nekeyvah, אם נקבה im nekeyvah לרבות תמורת בעלי מומין,
le-rabos tmuras ba'alei mumin, even the תמורה of a בעל מום. And
let's just read the wrap-up here. אמר ליה רב ספרא לאביי, amar
lei Rav Safra le-Abaye, it's a little funny exchange. So רב ספרא
Rav Safra says to אביי, Abaye, איפכא מנא? ipcha mana? Why do
you, why did I learn the אםs im the way I did?
The אם im from the זכר zachar is to tell me, this
is the way אביי Abaye understood the question, the אם im from
the זכר zachar is to tell me the ולד vlad of a
בעל מום and the אם im from נקבה nekeyvah is to tell
me the ולד vlad of a תמורה. Maybe I learn the אםs,
im maybe I reverse where I learn the אםs im from. That's
how אביי Abaye understood the question. So he says, what are you
talking about? מסתברא ממקום שנתרבתה תמורה תמימה נתרבתה תמורה בעלי מומין. mistabra
mi-makom she-nisrabsa tmura temima nisrabsa tmura ba'alei mumin. Of course, if the
זכר, zachar, if נקבה nekeyvah is coming to tell you the תמורה
of an unblemished, אם נקבה im nekeyvah is coming to tell you
the תמורה of a blemish. And if the זכר zachar is coming
to tell you the child of an unblemished, אם זכר im zachar
is coming to tell you the child of a blemish. Of course
you learn the אם im in the same context as the original
word. So he said, no, he says that wasn't my question. אמר
ליה הכי קאמינא לך ליכתוב אם זכר אם נקבה. amar lei hachi
ka-amina lach lichtov im zachar im nekeyvah. I wasn't asking why you
don't learn the אם im differently. Of course you're going to learn
the אם im in the context of the first word you're learning
it. אלא כולי קרא קאמינא. ela kulei kra ka-amina. I'm asking you
about the whole original דרשה. drasha. ואימא זכר לרבות את התמורה נקבה
לרבות את הולד. ve-eima zachar le-rabos es ha-tmura nekeyvah le-rabos es ha-vlad.
And you understand that there's a real point to this. It's not
just is it arbitrary. It's that you're going to include a child,
learn it from the word נקבה, nekeyvah, don't learn it from the
word זכר. zachar. So why are you saying זכר zachar is the
child and נקבה nekeyvah is the תמורה? So what's the answer? אמר
ליה ולד לשון זכר משמע תמורה לשון נקבה משמע. amar lei vlad
lashon zachar mashma tmura lashon nekeyvah mashma. Okay, ולד, vlad, ולד vlad
as a... okay, but ולד vlad is a rabbinic term. Hey, ולד
vlad is a male, so we're going to learn ולד vlad from
the word זכר, zachar, and תמורה is a female, so we're going
to learn תמורה, the gender of the word, not of the animal.
So because of the gender of the word, we're going to learn
תמורה from נקבה. nekeyvah. So we will pick up tomorrow with the
question about when it does source in a בעל מום, what's the
nature of the קדושה of the offspring and the תמורה, can it
be brought as a קרבן korban or not? So we will see
that tomorrow.